Finding Aid for Osher Lifelong Learning Institute (University of Michigan) records, 1987-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Osher Lifelong Learning Institute (University of Michigan) records 1987-2006
University of Michigan. Osher Lifelong Learning Institute.
0.75 linear feet
0746 Bimu 2
The University of Michigan Osher Lifelong Learning Institute (OLLI) is a volunteer group part of the Turner Geriatrics Center that provides learning opportunities for people over the age of 55 through a variety of formats, including distinguished lecture series, study groups, and mini-courses. OLLI records range from 1987-2006 and consist of founding documents, correspondence, newsletters, flyers and pamphlets, committees, and other records documenting its administrative and programming activities.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (Donor # 9849 ) was received from the unit in January 2007.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The record group is open without restriction.
The Osher Lifelong Learning Institute (OLLI) at the University of Michigan is a program established in 1987 by a group of Turner Geriatric Clinic volunteer peer counselors for people over the age of 55 who share the love of learning. Formerly named Learning in Retirement (LIR), the program is designed to enhance understanding of the world, its historic, cultural, and social aspects, through lectures, mini-courses and study groups. LIR was one of the first members of the Elderhostel Institute Network, one of the largest non-for-profit educational organizations for adults over the age of 55.
The first LIR Board was elected in 1989, which adopted a constitution and by-laws the next year. Of the eight board members, four are elected every year for two-year terms. Standing committees include long range planning, curriculum, public relations, membership, finance, nominating, and editorial committees. Each year, OLLI presents a distinguished lecturer series, lecture series focusing on a single topic, mini-courses taught by retired University educators or community experts, study groups led by volunteers, and special presentations including tours. Lectures and the distinguished lecturer series run on the same schedule as the University of Michigan: fall, winter, and spring/summer. A broad range of topics is covered, including philosophy, space exploration, politics, technology and computing, creative writing, government and world culture.
LIR was renamed the Osher Lifelong Learning Institute in the fall of 2006 after receiving a $100,000 grant from Bernard Osher, a philanthropist interested in providing older learners with resources. Membership is open to anyone over the age of 55 for a small fee. The Osher Lifelong Learning Institute has a website at: http://www.umlir.org/.
The University of Michigan Osher Lifelong Learning Institute (OLLI) records (0.75 linear feet) (1987-2006) document the founding of the organization, programming initiatives and descriptions since its beginning, and annual activities through its publications. OLLI records consist of newsletters, flyers and pamphlets, programming materials, committee agendas and minutes, correspondence, and a few photographs. The record group is arranged into five series: Administrative Files, Committees, Meetings, Photographs, and Published Materials.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Osher Lifelong Learning Institute.; Adult education--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Elderhostels--Michigan.; Older people.; Turner Geriatric Clinic.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Administrative Files
  Administrative Files (0.25 linear feet) (1987-2006) contain founding documents such as constitution and by-laws, membership lists, organizational histories, staff position descriptions, survey assessments, correspondence, and strategic planning documents. It also contains the application for the Bernard Osher grant, awarded in June 2006.
  - Bernard Osher Grant application, 2006 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1993-2004, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Elderhostel Institute Network (Box 1)
  - Founding documents (includes bylaws and constitution), 1988-2004 (Box 1)
  - Membership lists, 2001-2003 (Box 1)
  - Organizational histories, 1991-2002 (Box 1)
  - Position descriptions (Box 1)
  - Strategic planning, 2001-2002 (Box 1)
  - Survey Assessments, 1987, 2001 (Box 1)
- Committees
  Committees (5 folders) (1987-2003) contain minimal agendas, minutes, and notes from five internal committees. Among the most documented committees are the Curriculum Committee and the Editorial Committee of the Open Mind publication. Less documented committees include the Committee on Study Groups, Committee Structures, and the Long Range Planning Committee.
  - Committee on Study Groups, 1990-1993 (Box 1)
  - Committee Structures, 1987-1992 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum Committee, 1988-2003 (Box 1)
  - Editorial Committee of Open Mind, 1988-1991 (Box 1)
  - Long Range Planning Committee, 2001-2002 (Box 1)
- Meetings
  Meetings (3 folders) (1989, 1995, 2003) contain basic information as recorded through agendas, minutes, and notes on the 1989 Annual Meeting, a 1995 Board Meeting, and the 2003 Staff Retreat at Camp Michigania.
  - Annual Meeting, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Board Meeting, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Michigania Retreat, 2003 (Box 1)
- Photographs
  Photographs (5 photographs) (undated) include unidentified images taken at two committee meetings.
  - Committee meetings (5 photos) (Box 1)
- Published Materials
  Published Materials (0.25 linear feet) (1989-2006) include two newsletters documenting annual events and programming (An Occasional Newsletter and The Open Mind), programming material including course catalogs and lists of lectures, speakers, and mini-courses, and flyers and pamphlets. LIR also published two course packs: one on China and Japan and another on World War II oral histories. A few articles about LIR are also found in this series.
  - An Occasional Newsletter (scattered), 1993-2004 (Box 1)
  - Articles about Learning in Retirement (scattered) (Box 1)
  - China and Japan: The East Through Western Eyes (Box 1)
  - Course catalogs, 1993-2006 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Flyers and pamphlets, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Lists of lectures, speakers, mini-courses, 1987-2005 (Box 1)
  - Perspectives on WWII (Box 1)
  - The Open Mind (scattered), 1989-1991 (Box 1)